Hi, everyone.
Welcome to another episode of our podcast.
Today, I have the pleasure of speaking with Laurie Williams.
She's a Distinguished University Professor
at North Carolina State University in Raleigh, USA.
Laurie is one of the two first winners in 2009
of the ACM SIGSOFT Influential Educator Awards
for her contributions to software engineering
and computer science education.
Laurie leads the software engineering Realsearch research group
at NC State, which I visited in 2014-15.
Laurie is a co-director of the NSA Science of Security
Lablet at NC State.
She was one of the founders of the first XP Agile Conference,
XP Universe, in 2001 in Raleigh, which has now
grown into the Agile annual Conference.
She has published many papers in software engineering,
software security, as well as advised many PhD students.
She's also the lead author of the Pair Programming
Illuminated book.
Thank you very much for having accepted my invitation, Laurie.
It's a long list, but it's also an incomplete list
of all the things you have done in your career.
Would you like to add anything to this description of you
and your career?
No, thank you very much for that introduction,
and it's my pleasure to be here today.
OK, thank you.
And we're going to start talking about software security.
You have been working with software security
for a few years, and the question is,
can we trust most of the software we use every day?
Yeah, well, I mean, to be honest, no.
As a security researcher, we find software vulnerabilities
really in anything we look at, and I'm
thankful that we don't have more big problems
with security.
We have plenty of problems with security,
but I'm happy that it's not even worse,
because there are vulnerabilities everywhere, unfortunately.
Yes, yes, I know.
And what are some of the biggest challenges
that software developers face in this area?
Well, I mean, I think that the two basic fundamental problems
that software developers face, one
is they're not measured on producing secure software.
They're measured on producing software,
and so the security part can be just not prioritized
in trying to get a product out the door.
And sometimes management doesn't really
support slowing things down so that the product is
more secure, and I think that that's a big problem.
Along with that is just overwhelm.
So developers have lots of things
that they're measured on, like making software,
but making it perform well and be accessible and be secure.
There's a lot of things that the developers are all
trying to do at the same time.
And then another thing is, and we're
trying to work on this in education,
is educating people so they know how to develop securely
and really kind of transforming education
so that students don't come in and learn
how to develop software and then later develop secure software.
So develop secure software from the beginning.
That's just the way you do it.
But I think that developers have a lot of challenges right now
from an education standpoint, a prioritization standpoint,
from a pressure standpoint.
Exactly, exactly.
And how does your research and the research
that you do with your PhD students and colleagues
help software developers address those challenges?
So what we're trying to do with our work,
I mean, there's a number of things
that we're working to do, but it's trying to make it easier.
In the general case, trying to make
it easier to develop secure software
and to do it as efficiently as possible,
because it's a scarce resource, the attention that
can be put on software security.
And so how do you spend your time as efficiently
and effectively as possible?
So some of the things that we've done,
like we did a very large study on the efficiency
and effectiveness of vulnerability detection tools.
So like static analysis, dynamic analysis, penetration testing,
just looking at, of those, for the different types
of vulnerabilities, what's the most efficient way
to find that vulnerability?
What's the most effective way to find
a broad range of vulnerabilities?
So that's one aspect.
But also, like coming up with metrics
that the use of the metrics can point people
in the right direction for where to look in order
to find vulnerabilities.
A lot of what we're doing now is focused on the software supply
chain.
A lot of developers, really all developers,
get open source software and bring open source software
into their projects.
And attackers are now putting vulnerabilities
intentionally into the open source software.
And so how do you safely use open source software
to not be a victim of what the attackers are doing
and putting into the supply chain?
So we're coming at it from a lot of different angles.
And an additional question is, you
mentioned open source software.
But there is also software like those
generated by GitHub Copilot or Chat GPT.
Is that another concern, that people
will bring software vulnerabilities
from those softwares?
Yeah, absolutely.
It's something that it's a new research area, which
is vulnerabilities because of Chat GPT and other large language
models.
So it's a brand new thing that people are looking at.
There's really, sometimes with security,
there's intentional problems and then
some unintentional problems.
And to say, if I bring it back to supply chain,
then I'll come back to the Chat GPT.
But with supply chain, people have used open source software
for a long time.
And sometimes, developers, by accident,
will put a vulnerability into some open source package.
Like Log4j was a big one where some developer made
a mistake, and then attackers come along
and take advantage of that mistake
that the developers put in.
And then that causes a supply chain problem.
But that was no malicious intent on the part of the developer.
Similar with Chat GPT and large language models,
they're being trained on what's going on.
And so Copilot, even a couple of years ago,
got some bad press because it was generating
vulnerable code because that's what's out there.
So it's training on vulnerable code,
and then it generates vulnerable code.
And so that's something that we'll deal with with Chat GPT
and all of large language models as it's
used to generate code, which it will be used to generate code.
The other is intentionally the training
data being trained with injected vulnerable code.
And then the model will generate more code.
So again, there's this unintentional,
the fact that what's out there in training data
just happens to be vulnerable because that's what people
are generating these days.
And then also the unintentional or the intentional malicious
training data that's put in.
So yeah, there's definitely a lot of challenges
in the forefront there.
And what advice do you give to software engineers that
want to create secure software?
So the advice is to get educated as much as possible
so that you can write code that's secure
and abides by secure principles.
And try to get yourself to be engineering secure code
from the beginning.
It's always harder, much harder, to wait
until the tools tell you that your code is insecure,
and then you fix it.
And you've been finished for a long time,
and now you have to fix it.
So it's much, much more efficient to design
and architect secure projects from the beginning.
So the advice is really to be as educated as possible
and to, right from the beginning,
build with security in mind.
And which resources do you recommend
to those software engineers?
I remember that when I was at NC State,
there was a visit by Gary McGraw.
He had a book about that.
But this was nine years ago.
Right now, what can those software engineers do?
Is there, for instance, I know there is a journal, IEEE
security, but are there any books, sites?
What else?
Yeah, it's a great question.
Things change in security
so fast.
So it's hard to, and so books can hardly keep pace.
I really feel that the US government and NIST
and a lot of the government agencies
are actually putting out really good things.
So I guess when I think about where do I look,
I look for NIST, the US National Institute
for Standards and Technology and what they put out.
OWASP is a nonprofit organization
that puts out great resources.
The Cloud Native Foundation puts out a lot of good resources.
The Linux Foundation, OpenSSF, which
is Open Secure Software Framework, maybe.
I'm not sure.
OpenSSF puts out a lot of good resources.
And the reason that all of those things I find
are good resources are because it's not
one person coming up with it.
Everything goes out for public comment.
And it's consensus-based.
And they do tend to update over time.
And there are a lot of good things.
So in my class, I teach a software security class.
And every year, it's different, because everything changes
every year.
But those are my go-to places to go look for,
what am I going to teach this year, those particular sites.
Very good.
And now we are going to talk about Azure Software
Development.
You co-wrote a book on pair programming.
And you have also written many papers related
to Azure Software Development.
In fact, if you go to your Google Scholar profile,
nine out of your 10 most cited works there are related to Azure.
How did you get interested in Azure Software Development?
Yeah, so there's two things I'll say.
One is I worked for IBM before I went back to get my PhD.
And this was a bit ago.
It was, I guess, in the early 90s, so quite a long time ago.
And so I'm going to make some statements about IBM, which
are sure not true now.
But at the time, back in the early 90s, the software process
at IBM, as in many places, was very heavyweight, very
water-fallish, very step-by-step.
And it just didn't work, which is why
Agile came about in the first place.
But I had firsthand knowledge.
I experienced it in my workplace.
So when Agile came along, when I was a PhD student,
it was very appealing to me right away,
because I had lived the problems that Agile was addressing.
So it was very appealing to me for that.
And then also, I happened to be a PhD student looking
for a PhD topic at the right time.
And in that particular case, Alistair Coburn,
who was one of the Agile Manifesto signers,
was someone, when I was in University of Utah
in Salt Lake City, he was there.
And I had met with him.
And so he was the one who brought up this.
There wasn't even the name Agile at that point.
It was even before that.
And he came in and was talking about this new thing,
eXtreme Programming.
And my advisor got excited about it,
because he had been working at Hewlett Packard.
So just like the excitement, something brand new
sent me down that path.
And it worked for me.
Even after all these years, you're
saying nine out of the top 10 are from those days.
And your PhD was about pair programming, right?
Right.
Yeah, my PhD was about pair programming.
And again, my excitement and my, I
would say with pair programming specifically,
it was more my advisor's excitement.
He, in his lifetime, had done a lot of pair programming.
And when he heard about pair programming,
he was like, I've done that.
And so when you're a PhD student looking for a topic,
you're looking for the twinkle in your advisor's eye.
And then you go after that topic.
So that's how that happened.
And again, it worked for me.
Great, great.
And now, before a little bit of context,
I have a podcast in Portuguese, which
is only about women in computer science.
And we always ask this question because people, women, they,
at least I believe in the US too, but in Brazil,
it's a small minority of professionals.
And so who asked that?
Because we are curious about, you
want to know how did you get interested in computer science?
How was your education in the area?
As far as I know, you don't have a bachelor's degree
in computer science, right?
Right, yeah.
So my bachelor's degree is in industrial engineering.
And as I was heading towards school
and finishing high school, I wanted
to be a kindergarten teacher.
And I was pretty stubborn about that.
And then every year, my guidance counselor,
that's who we had in the US, who would give you advice on what
to do, was always saying, you're good in engineering
because my test results said that.
And my father was an engineer, and he wanted me to do it.
And I was, no, kindergarten teacher.
But the very last year of high school, I was like, fine.
I'll just do engineering.
And so I got an engineering degree and then went to work for IBM as an engineer, which was good.
I liked it. I didn't regret being a kindergarten teacher. I was happy with what I was doing.
But at IBM, they asked me to be the assistant to the lab director.
And so in that job, being with him all the time,
he had software people and hardware people, manufacturing people.
He had a variety of types of people in his organization and one of them being software.
And after my assignment being his assistant, then he said, what do you want to do next?
And so I said, software, I think that would be good.
And so then I did that and it was interesting.
And then when I left IBM and I knew I wanted to get a PhD at that point,
I knew I liked industrial engineering and I knew I liked computer science.
And then I was like, what should I do?
And it just seemed like computer science was more versatile, more flexible, probably more opportunities.
And so I chose computer science at that point.
And it did, you know, it is flexible and probably, you know, greater number of computer scientists.
And this is also related to a question that I asked in my other podcast.
And I have to say that the answers sometimes surprise me because as a man, I don't face the difficulties that the women face.
Did you face difficulties at school or at work that you feel they were because you are a woman?
Yeah, I think not as much in high school like so.
When I was coming up, like sometimes people, even as young as say 10, 11, 12, like girls along those lines start to get pushed in different directions.
I didn't actually face that.
I really think that the first place in my career or life when I faced problems from being a woman was in my PhD.
So not at IBM, you know, all the way until I got my PhD.
And at the time, as I got my PhD, in the four years it took me to get a PhD, which I did a pretty quick,
there were only two women in four years worth of class of PhD students.
It was only two women. And that was hard.
And it was hard. I was also had three children too.
So that that was made me different than the other students because generally it was males without children and I was a female with three children.
And it was hard.
But I think if I didn't have as much like determination that I'm getting this degree, no matter what you throw at me, I might not have done it.
I would, you know, I had a lot of things against me, not just being a woman, but I was an industrial engineer where everyone else was computer scientists.
I had children and they didn't. I was one of the few women.
So I had a lot of a lot of things that made it harder.
And I tried to give the faculty members who were basically all male the benefit of the doubt because I thought they just know how to work with men.
They don't know how to work with women like they aren't trying to do anything against me.
They just don't know what to do with me.
And the other thing is like a lesson that I learned is that it felt really hard for me when I did it.
And it felt like people were working against me.
But 17 years after I graduated, they invited me back to do a presentation and everyone was so happy to see me.
And so it made me think maybe it was just the pressure I was under that made me feel like they were working against me and they weren't at all.
And so it's just a good reminder that like it's our own interpretation of things.
Sometimes it's not reality. It's just the interpretation.
And do you participate? Do you take part in any support groups for women in computing?
I have participated in support groups and like I'll take advantage of anything like at conferences.
I might have a woman's thing and I'll go and support women in every day, every day that I can, that I do.
Something that I did back in my department was I was the department head, the interim department head at a time.
And I felt like the only reason that I did that, because I really like research, the only reason I really agreed to do that was to be an example to women.
So like there are times where I just do something just to be an example.
And like in that particular case, like there's this wall of all the department heads from the very beginning.
We've had, I think our department is now 55 years old.
So all the department heads from the last 55 years were all on the wall and they were all white men all the way down the hall.
And then when my picture got put up there, I thought my work is done here.
Now women can walk down the hall and know you could be a woman and do this too.
So I guess I have that mentality and with a lot of things I do is just to be there for women when I can and to be a role model in all ways that I can.
And what would you say to girls or women that want to follow a career in computing that might be listening to this podcast?
Yeah, well, I mean, take what I said earlier that even if it's hard for you to try to not take it personally,
to just keep trying to do your best and get with other women.
When I was teaching classes that had groups, and I still do, I always try to make sure that if there's one woman in a group, there's two.
And just support each other as much as you possibly can throughout the process.
Really to carry, so we carry each other through the process.
And if you get any, if you're feeling like you're getting any messages to say like women aren't as good at this or anything, just like forget it.
Don't even pay attention to it.
Don't take it personally, just keep doing your best and the right things will happen.
Great. And now I'm going to talk about another topic, which is advising and mentoring.
And as I already told listeners here, I have spent one year at your group.
And one curious thing about that is that all those PhD students that are now PhD people, they are professionals.
About half of those people are in industry, half in academia.
So you have advised at least 20 PhDs and some of whom work in the industry, Microsoft, SAS, IBM, Google, some in academia.
Did you serve as a mentor for them in deciding what to do after graduation?
So my advice to them always was to be as flexible as possible throughout.
Like I've had some that came in like I'm going to industry and they're in academia now and vice versa.
And so like I really my advice to them was like, don't make a decision.
Just do a good job, publish your papers and even go through the interview process with all industry and academia because you don't know.
I feel like when it comes to getting your first job after a PhD and maybe just getting your first job,
when you go to the interview, you know like this is where I'm supposed to be or this is not where I'm supposed to be.
And what I tell the students is like apply lots of places and let the universe decide.
Like let the world, like let life show you where you're supposed to be.
So if you decide yourself as a person, like I'm going to go to academia, you don't know.
But then if it turns out you applied to industry and academia and no one from industry interviews you,
then life has told you the right path for you is academia.
And then you can't question, you can't ever say, I wonder what would have happened if I had applied to Google or wonder what,
like you know what would have happened because you did it and then you can feel more confident with your choice.
And so really my advice to them always was just, you know, keep your options open,
which can means like some people can say I'm just going to go to industry and they might not focus as much on writing on publications because of that.
But then then they have decided for themselves.
And so rather that be flexible and keep your options open.
Great. So you are an important figure in the world of software engineering.
I know many people know you, for instance, I have interviewed in one of my podcasts,
Guilherme Travassos, and I mentioned you and he, oh, Laurie, Laurie, I know Laurie.
And, oh, by the way, we are going to have ICSE 2000, I believe ... 2027?
Oh, I'm not sure, but I'll put in the description. It's either 2024 or 2025.
No, I mean, so FSE is sooner, maybe 2026.
In Brazil?
Yeah, or 2025 maybe. But anyway.
Yes.
You're right. I think you're right. I think it's 2026 - ICSE and 2025 - FSE.
Yes, maybe you will come because you usually attend those big software engineering events in Rio de Janeiro.
But the question is for you, what's the next frontier in software engineering?
It can be something that you think will happen or something that you'd like to see happening in our field.
Yeah, I mean, so I guess from a software engineering standpoint, I mean, and I'm doing a talk at ICSE this year,
is really, I mean, I think that software should be secure and that you can't say the security people will do that,
that we could all consider ourselves security people.
So if you're in requirements or testing or whatnot, like everyone should consider security as part.
And that's what I would love for software engineering is just like we all do it.
Exactly. And I just confirmed it's 2026.
OK.
ICSE 2026 is going to be in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, for the first time in Brazil,
but not the first time in Latin America because I remember there was an ICSE on Buenos Aires, Argentina.
OK, thanks again for your time, Laurie.
Would you like to leave some final words for our audience?
Sure. I guess, you know, some of the things are, you know, when I think about some of the best advice that I've gotten,
there was one woman that I was my manager at IBM and I was a new, you know, just out of college.
And, you know, trying to navigate the world of being a professional.
And at the time, and maybe still today, there was a lot of pressure because I was women were a minority to act like a man.
And I thought I needed to do that.
And I was doing that as best I could.
But it wasn't natural.
And she said, you know, you're here too many hours of the day.
Just be yourself.
And that was great advice because then I could relax.
And actually, you know, I feel like I was just as successful as I would have been if I acted like a man.
And so my advice is like, just be yourself.
Do a good job.
And, you know, everything that that is supposed to happen should happen.
It's much more comfortable to be yourself.
Yes, great advice.
So thank you very much, everyone.
See you in the next episode of our podcast.
Thank you very much.